Vladimir Vladimirovich Nabokov Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Vladimir Vladimirovich Nabokov Papers 1918-1974 (bulk 1925-1965)
MSS34082
Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977
7,000 items 22 containers plus 1 oversize 8.4 linear feet 13 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Poet, novelist, literary critic, lecturer, and translator. Correspondence and notes with holograph and typescript drafts, galley proofs, page proofs, and printed versions of biographies, book reviews, essays, interviews, memoirs, novellas, novels, plays, poems, short stories, and translations of works by others.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1886-1957--Correspondence.; Aĭkhenvalʹd, I︠U︡. I. (I︠U︡liĭ Isaevich), 1872-1928--Correspondence.; Banks, Nathan, 1868- --Correspondence.; Baty, Gaston--Correspondence.; Berberova, Nina Nikolaevna--Correspondence.; Berdi︠a︡ev, Nikolaĭ, 1874-1948--Correspondence.; Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1870-1953--Correspondence.; Jannelli, Altagracia de--Correspondence.; Khodasevich, V. F. (Vladislav Felit︠s︡ianovich), 1886-1939--Correspondence.; Lukash, Ivan, 1892-1940--Correspondence.; Maklakov, V. A. (Vasiliĭ Alekseevich), 1870-1957--Correspondence.; Michener, Charles Duncan, 1918- --Correspondence.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977, tr. Eugene Onegin, a novel in verse. 1964.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977, tr. Song of Igor's campaign; an epic of the twelfth century. 1960.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Bend sinister. 1947.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Conclusive evidence, a memoir. 1951.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Defense. 1930.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Despair. 1936.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Event. 1938.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Gift. 1952.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Glory. 1932.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Invitation to a beheading. 1938.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Lolita. 1955.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Lolita: a screenplay. 1961.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Mary. 1926.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Pale fire. 1962.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Pole. 1924.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Real life of Sebastian Knight. 1941.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Tragedii︠a︡ gospodina Morna; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977. Waltz invention. 1938.; Pertzoff, Peter Alexander--Correspondence.; Priel, Jarl--Correspondence.; Rapchïnskiï, Borïs, 1887- --Correspondence.; Rudnev, V. V.--Correspondence.; Schakovskoy, Zinaïda, princesse, 1906-2001--Correspondence.; Struve, Gleb--Correspondence.; Zenzinov, V. (Vladimir), 1880-1953--Correspondence.
Subjects
Literature.; Motion picture plays.; Poetry.
Titles
Novoe russkoe slovo.; Petropolis.; Poslednie novosti.; Russki zapiski.; Sovremennye zapiski.
Occupations
Authors.; Critics.; Lecturers.; Translators.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Vladimir Vladimirovich Nabokov, poet, novelist, literary critic, lecturer, and translator, were donated to the Library of Congress by Nabokov from 1958 through 1965. Additions were acquired by purchase in 1971 and 1991 and by gifts from Peter Pertzoff in 1964 and Jay Wilson in 1991.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Vladimir Vladimirovich Nabokov are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on thirteen reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1899, Apr. 22 Born, St. Petersburg, Russia
1919-1922 Resided in England following the Russian Revolution
1922 B.A. in French and Russian literature, Trinity College, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, England Vladimir Dmitrievich Nabokov (father) assassinated
1922-1937 Maintained residence primarily in Berlin, Germany
1925 Married Véra Evseyevna Slonim
1926 Published Mashenʹka (Mary). Berlin: Slovo
1928 Published Korolʹ, dama, valet (King, Queen, Knave). Berlin: Slovo
1930 Published Zashchita Luzhina (The Defense). Berlin: Slovo
1932 Published Otchaianie (Despair). Berlin: Petropolis
1933 Published Podvig (Glory). Paris: Sovremennyia zapiski
1934 Dimitri Vladimirovich Nabokov (son) born
1937-1940 Maintained residence primarily in Paris, France
1937 Published Dar (The Gift) serially in Sovremennye zapiski, Paris, France
1938 Published Sobytie (The Event) serially in Russkie zapiski, Paris, France Published Izobretenie Valʹsa (The Waltz Invention) serially in Russkie zapiski, Paris, France Published Priglashenie na kaznʹ (Invitation to a Beheading). Paris: Dom Knigi
1940 Emigrated to United States with wife, who was of Jewish ancestry, and son to escape Nazi persecution
1941-1948 Lecturer in elementary Russian and Russian literature in translation, Wellesley College, Wellesley, Mass.
1941 Published The Real Life of Sebastian Knight. Norfolk, Conn.: New Directions
1944 Published Nikolai Gogol. Norfolk, Conn.: New Directions
1945 Granted United States citizenship
1947 Published Bend Sinister. New York: H. Holt
1948-1958 Professor of Russian and European literature, Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1951 Published Conclusive Evidence: A Memoir. New York: Harper
1952 Published Dar (The Gift). New York: Chekhova
1955 Published Lolita. Paris: Olympia Press
1957 Published Pnin. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday
1958-1977 Maintained residence primarily in Montreux, Switzerland
1960 Published The Song of Igor's Campaign. New York: Vintage Books
1962 Published Pale Fire. New York: Putnam
1964 Published Eugene Onegin. New York: Pantheon Books
1970 Published Speak, Memory: An Autobiography Revisited. New York: Capricorn Books
1974 Published Lolita: A Screenplay. New York: McGraw-Hill
1977, July 2 Died, Montreux, Switzerland
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Vladimir Vladimirovich Nabokov (1899-1977) span the years from 1918 to 1974, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period between 1925 and 1965. Focusing on Nabokov's work as a poet, novelist, literary critic, lecturer, and translator, the collection consists of the following series: Correspondence, Writings, Miscellany, an Addition, and Oversize containing holograph and typescript drafts, galley proofs, page proofs, and printed versions of biographies in addition to book reviews, essays, interviews, memoirs, novellas, novels, plays, poems, short stories, translations of works by others, and related material. The bulk of the collection is written in Russian and English. In most instances, titles of Nabokov's works are based on English translations of Russian citations appearing in Michael Juliar's Vladimir Nabokov: A Descriptive Bibliography. There are also small amounts of material in French and German. Additional Nabokov papers are in the Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library.
The Correspondence series is arranged as letters received and sent. Although small in quantity, it contains letters from prominent figures in Russian literature and culture including IU. I. Aikhenvalʹd, Mark Aleksandrovich Aldanov, Nina Nikolaevna Berberova, Nikolai Berdiaev, Ivan Alekseevich Bunin, Ivan Lukash, V. A. Maklakov, V. F. Khodasevich, Boris Rapchinskii, V. V. Rudnev, and V. Zenzinov. Various Russian-language emigré publishers and publications are also represented in the series, such as Petropolis, Novoe russkoe slovo, Poslednie novosti, Russki zapiski, and Sovremennye zapiski. Subjects include publication deadlines, copyright issues, and author's fees, as well as Nabokov's interest in butterflies. The letters of Gaston Baty and Jarl Priel discuss the performance possibilities of Nabokov's play Catastrophe, the French translation of Sobytie. Other correspondents include Peter Pertzoff, translator of works by Nabokov; Altagracia de Jannelli, Nabokov's literary agent in the United States; and lepidopterists Nathan Banks and Charles Duncan Michener.
The Writings series constitutes the largest portion of the collection. The bulk of the series consists of material relating to works of nonfiction, translations of works by others, and novels and reflects both the Russian and English language periods of the author. It was as a writer in English following his move to the United States in 1940 that Nabokov began to achieve serious recognition as a novelist. His writings were banned in the Soviet Union until the 1970s. Nabokov's first of several book-length autobiographies, Conclusive Evidence: A Memoir, is documented in files by that name. He regarded the process of translation as a serious literary endeavor, frequently quoting Aleksandr Sergeevich Pushkin's phrase: “Translators are the post horses of enlightenment.” While in America, Nabokov began to translate many of his earlier writings into English and, at times, made extensive revisions to the original text. Such is the case with Drugie berega, the Russian-language edition of Conclusive Evidence. Files related to Nabokov's English translation of Pushkin's novel in verse, Eugene Onegin, include material in which Nabokov reflected upon the translation process. The file also includes copious explanatory notes, extensive commentaries positioning the narrative within the context of European society during Pushkin's time, comments on the work's significance in Russian literature, remarks upon previous translations by others, and two lengthy appendices and an index. Additional material relating to Eugene Onegin is present in the Bollingen Foundation Records in the Manuscript Division. The series also contains files on Nabokov's translation of the anonymous Russian epic, The Song of Igor's Campaign.
Nabokov's considerable output of novels is documented in the Writings series. Titles representing his Russian period include Dar ( The Gift), Mashenʹka ( Mary), Otchaianie ( Despair), Podvig ( Glory), Priglashenie na kaznʹ ( Invitation to a Beheading), and Zashchita Luzhina ( The Defense). Those representing his American period include Bend Sinister, Lolita, Pale Fire, and The Real Life of Sebastian Knight. The Writings series also contains material relating to a number of plays written in Russian by Nabokov during his early years. These include Izobretenie Valʹsa ( The Waltz Invention), Polius ( The Pole), Sobytie ( The Event), and an unpublished work, “Tragediia Gospodina Morna” (“The Tragedy of Mr. Morn”). A sizeable amount of material documents the author's film adaptation of his novel Lolita entitled Lolita: A Screenplay.
Holograph and typescript drafts of numerous poems written by Nabokov throughout his career are in both Russian and English. Representative titles include “Bezumets” (“The Madman”), “Chto za nochʹ s pamiatʹiu sluchilosʹ?” (“What Happened Overnight to Memory?”), “K Rossii” (“To Russia”), “Probuzhdenie” (“The Awakening”), “Rasstrel” (“The Execution”), “Smertʹ” (“Death”), “Snovidenʹe” (“A Vision in a Dream”), and “Vesna” (“Spring”). The poetry section also contains examples of Nabokov's translations of poems written by others, including two in French, “Le bateau ivre” by Arthur Rimbaud and the anonymous “La bonne Lorraine” translated as “Pʹianyi korablʹ”and “La bonne Lorraine,” respectively. One in Russian, “Obezʹiana” by V. F. Khodasevich, was translated into English as “The Monkey.” Short stories and novellas represented in the series include “The Double Monster,” “Govoriat po russki” (“They Speak Russian”), “Mademoiselle O,” “Ozero, obkalo, bashnia” (Cloud, Castle, Lake”), “Pilʹgram” (“The Aurelian”), “Podlets” (“An Affair of Honor”), and “Tiazhelyi dym” (“Torpid Smoke”).
Miscellaneous items in the Writings series include short works such as book reviews, classroom teaching material, and essays. Many of the poems and short stories in the collection are signed “V. Sirin,” a pseudonym frequently used by Nabokov in Berlin and Paris during the 1920s and 1930s.
Scattered throughout the collection are notes and drafts written on 4" x 6" cards. Files documenting the writings Pale Fire, Lolita: A Screenplay, and “The Vane Sisters” consist entirely of these cards.
The Miscellany series includes a transcript of a radio interview with Nabokov. An addition to the collection contains letters from Nabokov to Princess Zinaïda Schakovskoy and Gleb Struve. Oversize material consists of Nabokov's diploma from the University of Cambridge and passports and related material removed from the Miscellany series.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in five series:
Correspondence, 1923-1952
Writings, 1918-1964
Miscellany, 1919-1942
Addition, 1923-1974
Oversize, 1919-1922
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm79034082
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 23,205
- Correspondence, 1923-1952 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Letters received and sent.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent, organization, or subject and chronologically therein.
  - Letters received (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - A. M. Heath & Co., 1935-1936
    - Aikhenvalʹd, IU. I., 1926, undated
    - Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1934-1938
    - Banks, Nathan, 1942
    - Baty, Gaston, 1938
    - Berberova, Nina Nikolaevna, 1931-1939
    - Berdiaev, Nikolai, 1939
    - Bertensson, Sergei, 1938
    - Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1938-1939
    - Chambers, D. L., 1939
    - Crémieux, Benjamin, 1939
    - Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H., 1942
    - Donich, Rostislav, 1939
    - East and West Association, 1942
    - Fondaminskii, Ilʹia, and Ant. Fridmann [?], 1933
    - Gessen, G., 1938
    - Gessen, I. V., 1938
    - Goudy, Alexander Porter, 1939
    - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., 1942-1951
    - Hirschberg, Bernhard, 1925
    - Holger Schildts Förlagsaktiebolag, 1936
    - Iablokova [?], Tatʹiana, 1938-1939
    - Institute of International Education, New York, N.Y., 1942
    - Jannelli, Altagracia de, 1935-1942
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1943, 1952
    - Kaun, Alexander, 1936
    - Khodasevich, V. F., 1937-1938
    - Kovarskii, I., 1935-1936
    - Laval, Karin de, 1937
    - Library of Congress, 1937
    - Lukash, Ivan, 1925-1926
    - Maklakov, V. A., 1937
    - Malozemova, E., 1938
    - Mann, Klaus, 1941
    - Michener, Charles Duncan, 1942
    - New Yorker, circa 1940s
    - Osorgin, Mikhail, 1933
    - Petropolis, publishers, 1934-1938
    - Pravdin, V., 1937
    - Priel, Jarl, 1938
    - Prismanova, Anna, undated
    - Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1938
    - Rapchinskii, Boris, 1936
    - Rosov, Samuil, 1936
    - Rostovtzeff, Michael Ivanovich, 1939
    - Rudnev, V. V. See same container and reel, Letters received, Sovremennye zapiski
    - Russkie zapiski, 1938-1939
    - Shakovskoi, Ioann, circa 1925, 1933
    - Slonim, Marc, 1935
    - Smeding, H. J., 1939
    - Sorokin, P. A., 1939
    - Sovremennye zapiski, 1937
    - Tolstoy, Alexandra, 1938
    - Ullstein GmbH, 1935
    - University of Leeds, Leeds, England, 1939
    - Unkovskii, V., 1938
    - Wereldbibliotheek-Vereening, 1939
    - Zelenskii, Filip, 1923
    - Zenzinov, V., 1935-1938
    - Unidentified, 1939-1942, undated
  - Letters sent
    - Fondaminskii, Ilʹia See same container and reel, Letters sent, Sovremennye zapiski
    - Klement, Otto, 1935
    - Kortner, Fritz, 1937
    - Life, 1943
    - Maklakov, V. A., 1938
    - Nikolajević, N., 1933
    - Novoe russkoe slovo, 1941
    - Pertzoff, Peter, 1933-1944, undated
    - Poslednie novosti, 1937
    - Rudnev, V. V. See same container and reel, Letters sent, Sovremennye zapiski
    - Rydelius, Ellen Victoria, 1937
    - Sovremennye zapiski, 1937
    - Vremea, publishers, 1939
    - Zenzinov, V. See same container and reel, Letters sent, Sovremennye zapiski
- Writings, 1918-1964 (Box 1-21, Reel 1-13)
  Drafts, proofs, and printed versions of biographies, book reviews, essays, memoirs, novellas, novels, plays, poems, short stories, and translations of works by others as well as correspondence and notes.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of writing, title, and type of material.
  - Fiction (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Novels
      - Bend Sinister
        - Book review by A. Nazaroff, broadcast on “Voice of America” radio, transcript in Russian, 1947
        - Draft in English, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 2)
      - Dar ( The Gift)
        - Drafts in Russian, undated
          - Chapters 1 and 4, (3 folders)
          - Fragments
          - Unpublished chapter drafts, (2 folders)
        - Printed version in Sovremennye zapiski in Russian, 1937-1938, (2 folders)
      - Kamera obskura ( Camera Obscura, 1936, and Laughter in the Dark, 1938), draft fragment in Russian, 1931
      - Korolʹ, dama, valet ( King, Queen, Knave), draft fragment in Russian, undated
      - Lolita, notes in English on 4"x 6" cards, 1950-1955 See also Containers 10-12, Reels 8-9, Lolita: A Screenplay, (6 folders)
      - Mashenʹka ( Mary), draft in Russian, circa 1925, (2 folders) (Box 3, Reel 3)
      - Otchaianie ( Despair), draft in Russian, 1932
      - Pale Fire, draft in English on 4"x 6" cards, 1957-1961, undated, (17 folders); (24 folders); (23 folders); (5 folders) (Box 4, Reel 4, Box 5, Box 6, Reel 5)
      - Pnin, notes in English, undated
      - Podvig ( Glory), draft in Russian, 1930, (2 folders)
      - Priglashenie na kaznʹ ( Invitation to a Beheading)
        - English edition, 1959
          - Draft, (5 folders); (1 folder) (Box 7, Reel 6)
          - Galley proofs, (3 folders)
          - Setting copy, (5 folders)
        - French edition, preface, page proofs, undated
        - Russian edition, draft, undated, (2 folders)
      - The Real Life of Sebastian Knight
        - English edition, draft, circa 1941
        - French edition, corrections to translation, undated
      - Zashchita Luzhina ( The Defense)
        - English edition, draft, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8, Reel 7)
        - Russian edition, draft fragments, undated
    - Short stories and novellas
      - “The Assistant Producer,” 1943
        - Draft in English
        - Notes in English on 4" x 6" cards
      - “Britva” (“The Razor”), drafts in Russian, undated, (2 folders)
      - “The Double Monster,” draft in English, 1950
      - “Double Talk,” draft in English, undated
      - “Govoriat po russki” (“They Speak Russian”), drafts in Russian, undated, (2 folders)
      - “Korolek” (“The Leonardo”), printed version in Poslednie novosti in Russian, 1933
      - “Lik”
        - Draft in Russian, 1938
        - Printed version in Russkie zapiski in Russian, 1938
      - “Mademoiselle O,” drafts in English, undated, (2 folders)
      - Nabokov's Dozen See Container 10, Reel 8, same heading
      - “Nabor” (“Recruitment”)
        - Draft in Russian, undated
        - Printed version in Poslednie novosti in Russian, 1935
      - “Natasha,” draft in Russian, 1927
      - “Obida” (“A Bad Day”), draft in Russian, 1931
      - “Ograda” [“Muzyka”] (“Music”), draft in Russian, undated
      - “Ozero, oblako, bashnia” (“Cloud, Castle, Lake”)
        - Draft in Russian, 1937
        - Printed version in Sovremennye zapiski in Russian, 1937
        - Translations
          - English
            - By Nabokov, “Song” from “Cloud, Castle, Lake,” new version, draft in Nabokov's hand, undated
            - By Peter Pertzoff, drafts, undated
              - Revised by Nabokov
              - With notes in Véra Nabokov's hand
          - French (“Mirage”), draft, undated
      - “Passazhir” (“The Passenger”), draft in Russian, 1927
      - “Pilʹgram” (“The Aurelian”)
        - Drafts in Russian (working title “Palomnik”), 1930, (2 folders)
        - Printed version in Russian with Nabokov's notes in English for English translation, undated
      - “Pisʹmo v Rossiiu” (“A Letter That Never Reached Russia”), draft in Russian, undated
      - [Po utram, esli solntse priglashalo menia...], draft fragment in Russian, undated
      - “Podlets” (“An Affair of Honor”), draft in Russian, 1927
      - “Poseshchenie muzeia” (“The Visit to the Museum”), printed version in Sovremennye zapiski in Russian, 1939
      - “Rozhdestvenskii rasskas” (“A Christmas Story”), draft in Russian, undated
      - “Sluchay iz zhizni” (“A Slice of Life”), draft in Russian, undated
      - “That in Aleppo Once...,” draft in English, undated
      - “Tiazhelyi dym” (“Torpid Smoke”), printed version in Poslednie novosti in Russian, 1935
      - “The Vane Sisters,” draft in English on 4" x 6" cards, undated, (4 folders)
      - “Vesna v Fialʹte” (“Spring in Fialta”) (Box 9)
        - Draft in Russian, 1936
        - English translation by Peter Pertzoff, draft revised by Nabokov in English, undated
      - “Zaniatoy chelovek” (“A Busy Man”), drafts in Russian, undated, (2 folders)
  - Nonfiction
    - Biography
      - Nikolai Gogol, corrections to translation, French edition, undated
    - Memoir
      - Conclusive Evidence: A Memoir
        - English edition
          - Foreword (not used), drafts, undated, (2 folders)
          - Chapter 1
            - Draft, undated
            - Galley proof corrections on 4" x 6" cards, undated
            - Notes, undated
          - Chapter 2, draft, 1949
          - Chapters 3, 8, 10-12, drafts, undated, (7 folders)
          - Chapter 15
            - Drafts, undated, (4 folders)
            - Galley proof corrections, undated
          - Chapter 16 (not used), disguised as anonymous review of Conclusive Evidence, draft, undated
            - General notes, undated, (3 folders)
            - Unidentified draft fragments, undated
        - Russian edition, Drugie berega, based upon translation of Conclusive Evidence into Russian by Nabokov
          - Foreword, draft, undated
          - Chapters 1-3, 7, drafts, undated, (4 folders)
          - Chapters 10, 12, 14, drafts, undated, (3 folders) (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Miscellaneous short writings
    - Book reviews by Nabokov
      - Belloc, Hilaire, unidentified, draft in English, undated
      - Bryant, Arthur, Pagent of England (1840-1940), draft in English, undated
      - Cournos, John, A Treasury of Classic Russian Literature, and Bernard Guilbert Guerney, An Anthology of Russian Literature, draft in English, circa 1962
      - Lifar, Serge, Serge Diaghilev, draft in English, circa 1940
      - Masefield, John, Basilissa, draft in English, undated
      - Maximoff, G. P., The Guillotine at Work, drafts in English, undated, (2 folders)
      - Rothenstein, John, Life and Death of Conder, draft in English, undated
      - Rustaveli, Shota, The Knight in the Tiger's Skin, draft in English, undated
      - Thaler, Alwin, Shakespeare and Democracy, and Alfred Harbage, Shakespeare's Audience, draft in English, undated
      - Williams, Frayne, Mr. Shakespeare of the Globe, draft in English, undated
      - Wright, J. F. C., Slava Bohu, The Story of the Dukhobors, draft in English, undated
    - Classroom teaching material
      - Creative writing course
        - Lecture notes on short stories, draft in English, undated
        - Lecture notes on style, draft in English, undated
      - Exam questions, draft in English, undated
    - Essays
      - “Opredeleniia” (“Definitions”), draft in Russian, 1940
      - “Vozzvanie o pomoshchi” (“Call for Help”), draft in Russian, undated